If anyone can kill you,
能夠取你性命的人
it's the Demon King
若不是魔王
or a human mage.
就是人類的魔法使喔
ORIGINAL STORY BY KANEHITO YAMADA / TSUKASA ABE
（原作：山田鐘人，作畫：阿部司）
She blocked it.
擋下來了
Not surprising.
如我所料
From here it will be
現在開始
a battle of attrition.
就進入消耗戰了
They really were here.
還真的有耶
It's just as Methode detected.
跟梅特戴感知到的一樣
Don't get in my way.
你別礙我的事啊
Right back at you.
那正是我要說的
Methode figured out the exact locations of our enemies.
梅特戴找出複製體的正確位置了
If it turns into a melee, we have no chance of winning.
變成混戰的話 我們就沒有贏的機會了
Let's split up and stop the clones
在複製體聚集到這裡之前
before they assemble here.
我們分頭去阻止它們吧
We've told each other who our toughest opponents would be.
吾等已經互相告知 彼此難以應付的對手
If it's a tough opponent for you,
如果是自認難以應付的對手
it should be a tough opponent for your clone as well.
那麼對你的複製體來說，也理應相同
In terms of being able to communicate and cooperate,
以我們擁有溝通與合作的能力來看
we have an advantage.
吾等佔了上風
If we choose who we fight wisely,
只要稍加思考，選擇適合的對手
we can have the upper hand to some extent.
就能取得一定程度的優勢
If you can't defeat them alone,
要是無法獨自打敗對手
try to outnumber them.
那就以量制勝
It's almost funny how easy it is to fight her.
跟她對戰真是輕鬆到可笑的地步
If we keep this up, we can stop the clones.
這樣應該就能阻止複製體了
Okay, let's go according to plan.
那麼我們就依計畫行事
All right. I wish you good luck.
好，祝兩位好運
There's one concern.
只是有一點令人擔心
The total number of clones I can detect
我所感知到的複製體總數
is less than the number of examinees.
比考生人數還要來得少
And what's more,
更重要的是
I cannot detect our biggest threat, which is Sense's clone.
我無法感知到 最有威脅性的冉則考官的複製體
You're right, I can't detect it either.
確實如此，我也感知不到
We can't overlook the existence of Sense's clone.
冉則的複製體不容我們小覷
If we get caught in crossfire, I won't be able to protect Fern.
要是遭到兩邊夾擊 我就保護不了費倫了
Worst-case scenario, we both may die.
最糟的情況是我們兩個人都會喪命
I'm not able to detect the locations of Fern and Denken's clones either.
我也感知不到 費倫小姐跟鄧肯先生的複製體
We have no choice but to use more accurate close-range detection.
只能改用更精確的近距離感知了
If you weren't here,
你要是沒有進來的話
we wouldn't have to worry about this.
我們就不必擔心這點了
First-class mages must be able to
一級魔法使就是身處
overcome even the most absurd adversities.
最為險惡的逆境也能夠有本事克服
This doesn't even count as adversity.
這種情況連逆境都算不上
Plus, you get to pass the exam just by covering each other's backs.
而且你們只要守護夥伴 互相照應就能合格
It is such an easy, peaceful exam.
可以算是相當簡單又和平的考試了
We defeated it.
打倒了
But it's not the greatest feeling.
但感覺還真不舒服
A surprise attack?
偷襲？
What a monster…
真是怪物…
I don't remember stopping my mana detection.
我明明不曾中斷過魔力感知啊
Lawine, you should break your bottle too.
拉比涅，你也打破瓶子吧
You're mature enough to know your limits, aren't you?
你不是那種不知進退分寸的小鬼吧？
There will be another exam in three years.
三年後還會有考試
Damn it!
可惡！
I didn't make it in time, huh?
還是沒趕上嗎？
But the outcome wouldn't have been any different
但就算多了老夫一個助手
even if I had assisted them.
結果應該也一樣
Even while her back is facing me, I don't see any window of opportunity.
儘管她現在背對我 我也看不出絲毫破綻
In any case, I still need to at least buy some time.
無所謂了，能爭取多少時間算多少
Aren't you Denken, the Imperial Mage?
你不是宮廷魔法使鄧肯嗎？
What's the situation?
現在是什麼情況啊？
Are you planning on fighting that thing?
難道你想跟那玩意戰鬥嗎？
I don't think you will win.
我覺得你沒有勝算喔
I am aware of that.
這點我也知道
Hey, Denken, is this a necessary step in raiding the dungeon?
喂，鄧肯 想攻克迷宮就必須要打倒它嗎？
Right now, Frieren is--
芙莉蓮現在正…
I don't need an explanation. Is this a necessary step or not?
不用解釋了，是不是一定要打倒它？
It is.
是
Then I'll defeat it.
那就交給我吧
What are you talking about?
你在說什麼啊？
Denken is the strongest among us.
在場的人之中，最強的就是鄧肯
And first of all, you couldn't even win against Wirbel.
況且你不是連威亞貝爾都沒打贏嗎？
That's not what this is about, though.
此一時非彼一時哦
Indeed, I am an inexperienced third-class mage.
我的確還是個經驗不足的三級魔法使
I am substantially weaker than Denken and Wirbel.
實力肯定不如鄧肯跟威亞貝爾
But I'm pretty sure I can win against Sense.
但就算這樣 我還是有十足的把握能打倒冉則
This is the spell I specialize in.
我專精的魔法就是這個
Reelseiden, a spell that can cut through pretty much anything.
“大概什麼都能砍的魔法”
It will cut through anything that I deem cuttable.
只要我認為能切開的東西 就一定能切開
And it will not cut anything that I deem uncuttable.
我若認為切不開的東西就一定切不開
So what?
那又怎樣？
Defensive magic can easily block that spell.
用防禦魔法就可以輕易擋下來了
Oh, that's right,
眼鏡男，說起來
you were watching me fight Wirbel.
你看過我跟威亞貝爾對戰吧
Well, defensive magic is made to block magic, after all.
也是，畢竟防禦魔法 就是為了擋住魔法而生的
I can't really visualize myself cutting through it.
我也無法真的 想像自己把它切開的畫面
Is that right?
是嗎？
Then it won't work against Sense either way.
那麼不管怎樣 你的魔法對冉則就沒有作用
Just from what I can detect, that hair is covered
就我所感知到的，那些頭髮
with multiple layers of magic that work like defensive magic.
覆蓋了多層媲美防禦魔法的魔法
Like I said, I don't care about all that logical stuff.
所以說，不管哪種推論都無所謂
It's all about visualizing.
這純粹是想像的問題
Hey, wait.
喂，等等
As I thought, Sorganeil won't work.
如我所料 將看見的人進行拘禁的魔法沒有作用
Hair is part of the body, after all.
說到底，頭髮也是身體的一部份
It's impossible to keep her entire body within sight.
要能將她全身納入眼底是不可能的
Reelseiden.
大概什麼都能砍的魔法
As expected, Übel is the one fighting my clone, huh?
我的對手果然是尤蓓爾嗎？
I already know the outcome.
誰贏誰輸一目瞭然
It probably won't even escalate into a battle.
恐怕連戰鬥都稱不上
That was two years ago, during the second-class mage exam…
那是兩年前 二級魔法使選拔測驗發生的事
The proctor assigned to the second stage of the exam
負責第二階段考試的考官
was Burg, a first-class mage.
是一級魔法使，布魯格
Since the time he became a first-class mage,
他自從成為一級魔法使之後
he had never once suffered a single wound during battle.
一次都不曾在戰鬥中受過傷
He was a mage who specialized in defensive magic.
是位專精於防禦魔法的魔法使
The Immovable Cloak.
“不動的外套”
It's a cloak he made from magic
是用魔法所製成的
that was embedded with defensive spells that repelled all offensive magic.
具有能夠擊退 所有攻擊魔法的防禦魔法
For the second stage of the exam,
在考試的第二階段裡
the examinees were to aim offensive magic at the cloaked Burg,
考生要對穿著外套的布魯格 發動攻擊魔法
and they simply had to make him take a step back to pass.
只要能讓他後退一步就算合格
The rule prohibiting the act of killing
考試規定禁止傷及性命
was only there to keep their offensive magic
目的在於控制攻擊魔法
under control for the safety of the other examinees.
保障其他考生的安全
Next.
下一位
Nobody was worried about Burg's safety.
沒有人擔心過布魯格的安危
I cut too much.
我切過頭了
But a nameless girl who was a newly appointed third-class mage
然而一個新晉三級魔法使的無名少女
killed him like it was nothing.
輕輕鬆鬆就殺了他
I'm disqualified, aren't I? I know.
我考試不合格吧？我知道
Can I go home now?
我能走了嗎？
I just have one question.
我只有一個問題
Go ahead.
請說
How were you able to break through the Immovable Cloak?
你是如何突破不動的外套的？
Um, have you ever done any sewing, Sense?
那個嘛，冉則大人 做過裁縫之類的工作嗎？
No. What about it?
沒有，這有什麼關係嗎？
I thought so. You look like your family is well-off.
看來你的出身相當富裕啊
Or maybe you use magic to take care of all that stuff?
還是那些事情全都用魔法解決了？
Well, you know,
不過說來慚愧
I'm clumsy, so I've never done it myself either.
我的手並不靈巧 所以也沒有做過裁縫
But I used to watch my older sister sew all the time.
但我總是在看姊姊做裁縫
When you cut the fabric,
剪裁布料的時候
you place the scissors like this and slice it in one sweep.
就會這樣拿著剪刀 然後唰一下剪過去
It makes a wonderful sound.
那種聲音真是悅耳
I loved that sound.
我非常喜歡那個聲音
Where are you going with this?
我不明白你想說什麼
I'm talking about visualization.
我在說想像的畫面啊
Fabrics are made to be cut.
布料這種東西就是拿來剪的
It's only natural to cut them.
剪開布料是理所當然的事情
She is crazy.
這個人簡直瘋了
It's true that anyone can visualize themselves cutting fabric.
的確不管是誰 都能想像剪裁布料的畫面
Even a fool can do that.
這種事連笨蛋都能做到
But the world of magic isn't that easy.
但是魔法的世界沒那麼簡單
If you cannot perfectly visualize it, you cannot actualize it with magic.
如果不能構築出畫面 就無法用魔法實現
Just as a tiny ant can't visualize itself stomping on a huge dragon,
好比小螞蟻 無法想像自己踩扁巨龍的畫面
hardly any mage could visualize
也幾乎沒有魔法使能夠想像
themselves cutting that cloak, which was protected by
那件受到銅牆鐵壁般的魔法 所保護的外套
impenetrable defensive spells.
能夠被自己切開的畫面吧
That's because any mage could tell at first glance that the cloak
其實隨便哪個魔法使 都能一眼就看出來
could repel any kind of offensive magic.
那件外套能擊退任何攻擊魔法
Even a fool could understand.
這點即便是個笨蛋都能懂
So long as humans are intelligent life forms,
正因人類是具有智慧的生命體
we cannot break free from those mental constraints.
所以無法隨意打破這種心理框架
And yet, she still followed her intuition.
然而，她卻依舊能遵從自己的感覺
Intellectually, she knew it was uncuttable.
理智上她很清楚那是無法切開的東西
But she trusted her intuition and visualized herself cutting the cloak.
但是她卻能信任自己的直覺 構築出切開外套的畫面
Her mental state cannot be that of a normal human being.
這種心理狀態已經不是正常人類了
It's a gift, at this point.
這可以稱得上是天賦的範圍了
Can I leave now?
我現在可以走了嗎？
Sure.
可以
By the way, Sense, you have such beautiful hair.
話說回來，冉則大人 你那頭秀髮很漂亮呢
Maintaining it must be a lot of work.
保養起來很費工夫吧
Perhaps I had already lost at that moment.
說不定那時候我就已經輸了
I cannot visualize myself winning against Übel.
我完全想像不出 自己打倒尤蓓爾的畫面
We are just too incompatible.
我們正好一物剋一物
Everyone needs to stop overcomplicating things.
大家把事情看得太複雜了
Hair is meant to be cut, isn't it?
頭髮就是拿來剪的東西，不是嗎？
Maintaining my hair?
保養頭髮嗎？
It's a hellish process.
簡直就像走一回地獄呢
I don't even want to think about it.
我根本不想想像那畫面
She should just cut it.
還不如剪掉算了
I see what's going on now.
我明白現在的狀況了
So all of you are buying time until
所以你們所有人都在爭取時間
Frieren defeats Spiegel, huh?
直到芙莉蓮 擊敗水鏡的惡魔，是嗎？
Yes, that's right.
是的，正是如此
We already took out three clones ourselves.
我們已經打敗我們三人的複製體了
Then that saves us time.
那樣的話就更省事了
Well then… Oh, my…
接下來…天啊
It seems Sense's clone was defeated just now.
看來剛剛有人打敗了冉則的複製體
This mana belongs to…
這股魔力是…
It was Übel, the third-class mage, who defeated it.
打敗它的是三級魔法使尤蓓爾
That's surprising.
真是令人意外的結果
Is it? They seem pretty incompatible.
是嗎？她們正好一物剋一物
Battles between mages are a bit like playing rock, paper, scissors.
魔法使之間的戰鬥就跟猜拳一樣
Although it's a complex and difficult version
只是是擁有無限可能
of rock, paper, scissors, with countless possibilities.
複雜又困難版的猜拳罷了
And now you want to expand the possibilities even more, huh?
所以你打算再多增加一點可能性嗎？
All right, I'll help you in holding back the clones.
可以啊，我會幫你們拖住複製體
I'm not the type to trust others,
我不太相信別人
but I'm not stupid enough to waste an opportunity.
但也沒蠢到浪費送上門來的機會
At the moment, there are two high-risk clones that
目前有兩個危險度很高的複製體
we must stop at all costs.
需要我們全力攔住
I have located
我已經找出
one of the two, which is Denken's clone.
兩者之一，也就是鄧肯先生的複製體
I will leave that one up to you three.
這一個就拜託你們三位了
In regard to the other one, which is Fern's clone,
至於另一個費倫小姐的複製體
you can leave that up to me.
就交給我來對付吧
It seems she is especially good at concealing her mana.
那孩子貌似很擅長隱藏魔力
Unless I find her, we may suffer
不趕緊找到她的話
casualties from surprise attacks.
很可能就會有人遭到突襲而喪命
Can you really handle her alone?
你一個人對付她沒問題嗎？
I can concentrate on mana detection better when I'm alone.
我獨自一人更能專注進行魔力感知
That girl is pretty strong, you know?
那孩子還蠻強的哦
I'm versatile, so stalling people is what I excel at.
我很能隨機應變 拖住別人正是我最擅長的事
-Plus, I tested my restraining spell. -There!
-而且我之前試過我的拘束魔法 -我戳！
-Made sure it worked on her. -I can't move.
-對她本人確實有效 -動不了了
All right then, let's get this started.
好，來大幹一場吧
Übel, this isn't
尤蓓爾，這個
my imagination, is it?
應該不是我的想像吧？
I don't think so.
應該不是喔
After all, you can't move, right?
畢竟眼鏡男你動不了了吧？
My clone has reemerged.
我的複製體復活了
Is this perhaps going to
這種情形莫非
continue until that Spiegel or whatever is defeated?
會持續到水鏡的惡魔被打倒為止？
It's a battle of attrition. This is getting exciting!
是消耗戰呢，事情開始變得有趣了！
Indeed…
真是的…
Now is the time to call it quits.
是時候該撤退了吧
This opening won't work either.
這個空隙也不行
Fern isn't able to notice it yet.
現在的費倫還沒辦法抓住這個時機
I'm left with no other choice.
果然只能這麼做了
The opening created after my mana detection is
光靠我的魔力感知中斷的空隙
interrupted won't be enough to kill the clone.
根本不足以打倒它
I agree.
的確如此
If only there was a bigger opening, we could win…
如果空隙時間更長就可以打贏了…
You think you can win?
你認為有勝算嗎？
Then I will create an opening.
那就由我來製造空隙
You can do such a thing?
您可以辦到那種事嗎？
The moment I become vulnerable,
在我露出可乘之機時
the clone will be even more vulnerable.
複製體露出的破綻會更大
But that means you will be…
但那就表示芙莉蓮大人會…
If I focus on my defense, nothing will become fatal.
只要我全力防禦就不會受到致命傷
What's the plan in that case?
那這種作戰要怎麼進行？
I'll leave that up to you.
這點就交給你了
If you think you can win, you will win.
你認為能贏的話，就一定能贏
How can you be so sure?
您怎麼能如此肯定呢？
Because I always underestimate you, Fern.
因為我總是會低估費倫你啊
That's good.
那還真是太好了
We have a chance of winning then.
這樣就有充分的勝算了
It's still standing…
還沒倒下，但已經受重傷了
Let's end this…
趕緊結束吧
What just happened?
剛剛是怎麼回事？
Was I attacked?
我被攻擊了？
I don't sense any mana at all.
完全感知不到半點魔力
My body isn't recognizing this attack as magic.
身體沒意識到這道攻擊是魔法
You're amazing, Mistress Frieren.
芙莉蓮大人真是厲害
So this is the highest form of magic?
這就是魔法的高度嗎？
But it's uncharacteristic of you…
但是這真不像您…
You're completely vulnerable.
完全破綻百出呢
Well done, Fern.
做得好，費倫
It's been 80 years since the last time I was forced into using that move.
我已經有八十年 沒有被逼到這步田地了
Well then, let's get this over with already.
那麼，趕緊結束這一切吧
So it ended?
結束了嗎？
I can't move anymore.
我再也動不了了
Wirbel, carry me please…
威亞貝爾，拜託揹我…
You two are constantly worn out.
你們兩個怎麼老是這樣啊？
So this is the innermost depths of the Ruins of the King's Tomb?
這就是零落的王墓的最深處嗎？
You have raided the Ruins of the King's Tomb.
各位已經成功攻克了零落的王墓
That makes you equivalent to a first-class mage.
這是足以媲美一級魔法使的成就
Your names will go down in history for this achievement.
各位將會因此而名垂青史
As promised, everyone who made it to the innermost depths
按照之前說好的 成功抵達最深處的所有人
will pass the second stage.
第二階段考試就合格了
And where did the greatest contributor to our success go?
話說回來，最大功臣跑到哪裡去了？
It's so dark!
好黑啊！
It's scary!
好可怕啊！
It's dark… So scary…
好黑啊，好可怕啊…
Well, I might do the same thing.
我懂這種感覺
Well then, the second stage of the exam is over.
那麼，第二階段考試就到此結束
Can you believe that it can even use healing magic?
誰能想到它還會用回復魔法啊？
See? Isn't it amazing?
怎麼樣？很厲害吧？
I guess.
嗯
Who are you?
你誰啊？
-We've been together. -You were unlucky.
-從我還小的時候 -你真倒楣
-Since I was small. -Flamme's spell.
-就一直陪在我身邊了 -弗蘭梅的魔法
-I'm in a terrible mood. -This will take time.
-我心情很不好 -這會花點時間
-Let's begin the third stage. -Fern.
-第三階段考試開始 -費倫
-Let's go back. -Make fun of me like you always do.
-回去吧 -像以往那樣笑我啊
"An Era of Humans."
《人類的時代》
Subtitle translation by: Kiko Morita
字幕翻譯：洪貞韻